Hugh Johnston fonds
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department
- Radical Campus files, 1958 - 2004; F-223-1; 2.55 m of textual records 72 sound recordings; Date range: Predominant dates of textual material in the series are 1965-1974. General note: sound recordings are located in series F-223-1-7-2.
  - Background material - Chapters 1, 2 and 3, 1958 - 2004; F-223-1-1; 1.11 m of textual records
    - Files on subjects, 1962 - 2004; F-223-1-1-4; 23 cm of textual records
      - Business Faculty, 1996; F-223-1-1-4-4 (Archival box - standard 223-8)
        Beedie School of Business; Textual records
      - Berkeley - University of California, 2000 - 2004; F-223-1-1-4-5 (Archival box - standard 223-8)
        University of California; Textual records
      - Campus Security, 2000 - 2001; F-223-1-1-4-6 (Archival box - standard 223-8)
        Campus Security Department; Textual records
      - Canadianization, 1969 - 1990; F-223-1-1-4-7 (Archival box - standard 223-8)
      - Communications Centre, 1965; F-223-1-1-4-8 (Archival box - standard 223-8)
        School for the Contemporary Arts; Textual records
      - Community colleges, 1968 - 2002; F-223-1-1-4-9 (Archival box - standard 223-8)
      - Computing science, 1973; F-223-1-1-4-10 (Archival box - standard 223-8)
        School of Computing Science; Textual records
      - Crisis in higher education, 1966 - 1977; F-223-1-1-4-11 (Archival box - standard 223-8)
      - Daycare, 1975 - 2000; F-223-1-1-4-12 (Archival box - standard 223-8)
        Daycare Centre; Textual records
      - Department heads - recruitment, 2000 - 2004; F-223-1-1-4-13 (Archival box - standard 223-8)
        File consists of handwritten notes summarizes the contents of documents from selected files held in SFU Archives in various fonds, including the President's Office (F-193), the Gordon Shrum fonds (F-32), Chancellor's Office (F-3), the Board of Governors (F-33), the McTaggart-Cowan fonds (F-65).
        Restricted in whole
      - Diamond University Club, 1971 - 1998; F-223-1-1-4-14 (Archival box - standard 223-8)
        Diamond University Club; Textual records
      - Dismissal procedures, 1970 - 1975; F-223-1-1-4-15 (Archival box - standard 223-8)
      - Faculty association, 1967 - 1968; F-223-1-1-4-16 (Archival box - standard 223-8)
        Simon Fraser University Faculty Association; Textual records
      - Faculty workload, 1971; F-223-1-1-4-17 (Archival box - standard 223-8)
      - First Nations education, 2000; F-223-1-1-4-18 (Archival box - standard 223-8)
      - Graduate Studies, 1965 - 1998; F-223-1-1-4-19 (Archival box - standard 223-8)
        Office of the Dean of Graduate Studies; Textual records
      - Geography department, 1969 - 1988; F-223-1-1-4-20 (Archival box - standard 223-8)
        Department of Geography; Textual records
      - Harrassment, 1987 - 1998; F-223-1-1-4-21 (Archival box - standard 223-8)
        Human Rights Office; Textual records
      - Harbour Centre, 1988; F-223-1-1-4-22 (Archival box - standard 223-8)
        SFU Vancouver; Textual records
      - History department, 1972 - 1996; F-223-1-1-4-23 (Archival box - standard 223-8)
        Department of History; Textual records
      - Institute for Public Policy Analysis, 1972 - 1974; F-223-1-1-4-24 (Archival box - standard 223-8)
        Institute of Public Policy Analysis; Textual records
      - Interdisciplinary Studies, 1972; F-223-1-1-4-25 (Archival box - standard 223-8)
        Faculty of Interdisciplinary Studies; Textual records
      - Library, 1964; F-223-1-1-4-26 (Archival box - standard 223-8)
        University Library; Textual records
      - Liquor policy, 1969 - 1970; F-223-1-1-4-27 (Archival box - standard 223-8)
      - MacDonald report, 2000 - 2004; F-223-1-1-4-28 (Archival box - standard 223-9)
        Macdonald, John B.; Textual records
      - MacLeans' university survey, 1996 - 1998; F-223-1-1-4-29 (Archival box - standard 223-9)
        Maclean's Magazine; Textual records
      - Maggie Benston Centre, 1996; F-223-1-1-4-30 (Archival box - standard 223-9)
      - McTaggart-Cowan - other universities, 1966; F-223-1-1-4-31 (Archival box - standard 223-9)
      - PSA affair, 1969 - 1974; F-223-1-1-4-32 (Archival box - standard 223-9)
        Department of Political Science, Sociology and Anthropology; Textual records
      - PSA - Fisher material, 1962; F-223-1-1-4-33 (Archival box - standard 223-9)
      - PSA - Ron McPhedran's honours essay, 2002; F-223-1-1-4-34 (Archival box - standard 223-9)
        Department of Political Science, Sociology and Anthropology; McPhedran, Ron; Textual records
      - PSA - Palmer decision, 1970; F-223-1-1-4-35 (Archival box - standard 223-9)
      - PSA- Peak article, 1994; F-223-1-1-4-36 (Archival box - standard 223-9)
      - SFU - Enrollment, 1965 - 1968; F-223-1-1-4-37 (Archival box - standard 223-9)
      - SFU - Pipe band, 1996; F-223-1-1-4-38 (Archival box - standard 223-9)
        Simon Fraser University Pipe Band; Textual records
      - SFU - radicalism, 1982 - 1998; F-223-1-1-4-39 (Archival box - standard 223-9)
      - SFU - statement of purpose, 1998; F-223-1-1-4-40 (Archival box - standard 223-9)
      - SFU - Statistics, 1999 - 2002; F-223-1-1-4-41 (Archival box - standard 223-9)
      - SFSS - Pornography Scandal, 1996 - 1997; F-223-1-1-4-42 (Archival box - standard 223-9)
        Simon Fraser Student Society; Textual records
      - Spanish and Latin American Studies department, 2001; F-223-1-1-4-43 (Archival box - standard 223-9)
        Department of Spanish and Latin American Studies; Textual records
      - Student attrition at SFU, 1965-1970, 1974; F-223-1-1-4-44 (Archival box - standard 223-9)
      - Student radicalism, 1965 - 2001; F-223-1-1-4-45 (Archival box - standard 223-9)
      - Teaching Support Staff Union - TSSU, 1974 - 2004; F-223-1-1-4-46 (Archival box - standard 223-9)
        Teaching Support Staff Union; Textual records
      - Trimester system, 1964 - 1971; F-223-1-1-4-47 (Archival box - standard 223-9)
      - Tuition, 1963 - 2004; F-223-1-1-4-48 (Archival box - standard 223-9)
      - University Act, 1963 - [200-?]; F-223-1-1-4-49 (Archival box - standard 223-9)
      - University of British Columbia, 2000 - 2004; F-223-1-1-4-50 (Archival box - standard 223-9)
        University of British Columbia (UBC); Textual records
      - Women's Studies, 1973 - 1996; F-223-1-1-4-51 (Archival box - standard 223-9)
        Department of Gender, Sexuality, and Women's Studies; Textual records
  - Background material - Chapters 4, 5 and 6, 1965 - 2004; F-223-1-2; 41 cm of textual records
    Sub-series consists of photocopied source material for chapters four, five, and six of Radical Campus. Subjects, events and activities documented include student conduct; student affairs; student activism; student associations; faculty associations; SFU governance; academic departments; prominent members of the SFU community; university disputes; and the Women's Movement. Sub-series includes memoranda; issues of the Peak; correspondence; minutes; newsletters; newspaper and journal articles; reports; research notes; briefs; and an index for the material compiled by Hugh Johnston.
    - Photocopies from the Peak, 1966 - 1977; F-223-1-2-1; 15 cm of textual records
      Sub-sub-series consists of several hundred full-page photocopies from The Peak relating to the governance of Simon Fraser University; student affairs; student activism; and academic freedom and tenure. These issues of the Peak are in chronological order. Hugh Johnston referred to these by creating a rough index of articles identified by the page and date of the Peak issues. This index is provided in pages 65-77 of the Yellow Notebook in sub-sub-series three. Subjects, events and activities documented include anti-war rallies and draft dodgers; athletics; football; tuition, student loans and bursaries; the BC Union of Students; Canadian Union of Students (CUS); the Canadian Association of University Teachers (CAUT) and the Association of University and Colleges of Canada (AUCC); the Faculty Association; Food Services; residences; registration; Graduate Student Society; the PSA affair; Students for a Democratic Society (SDS); Students for a Democratic University (SDU); the Shell service station dispute; the student movement; the Simon Fraser Student Society; and the Women's Movement.
      British Columbia Union of Students; Canadian Union of Students; Canadian Association of University Teachers; Association of Universities and Colleges of Canada; Simon Fraser University Faculty Association; Food Services; Students for a Democratic Society; Students for a Democratic University; Simon Fraser Student Society
      - Photocopies from The Peak, 1966; F-223-1-2-1-1 (Newspaper box 223-20)
      - Photocopies from The Peak, 1967; F-223-1-2-1-2 (Newspaper box 223-20)
      - Photocopies from The Peak, 1968; F-223-1-2-1-3 (Newspaper box 223-20)
      - Photocopies from The Peak, 1969; F-223-1-2-1-4 (Newspaper box 223-20)
      - Photocopies from The Peak, 1970; F-223-1-2-1-5 (Newspaper box 223-21)
      - Photocopies from The Peak, 1971; F-223-1-2-1-6 (Newspaper box 223-21)
      - Photocopies from The Peak, 1972; F-223-1-2-1-7 (Newspaper box 223-21)
      - Photocopies from The Peak, 1973; F-223-1-2-1-8 (Newspaper box 223-21)
      - Photocopies from The Peak, 1974; F-223-1-2-1-9 (Newspaper box 223-21)
      - Photocopies from The Peak, 1977; F-223-1-2-1-10 (Newspaper box 223-21)
    - Photocopies from fonds, 1965 - 2003; F-223-1-2-2; 21 cm of textual records
      Sub-sub-series consists of photocopied material from fonds held in the SFU Archives relating to The Peak; the Simon Fraser Student Society; Athletics and the TSSU. Hugh Johnston numbered each page of this material and created a rough index. This index is provided in pages 79-96 of the Yellow Notebook contained within sub-sub-series three. Subjects, activities and events documented include student conduct; the Student Affairs Committee; student activism; SFU Athletic programs; student clubs; health services; campus radio station; enrollment; faculty and student housing; the PSA affair; the Shell gas station affair; SFSS Presidents Stan Wong, Martin Loney, Rob Walsh, and Ian Spencer; the "Dentists' Wives"; the formation of TSSU; sabbatical eligibility; the presidencies of Kenneth Strand and Patrick McTaggart-Cowan; and the Women's Movement at SFU. Records include briefs, convocation programs, correspondence, journal articles, memoranda, minutes, newsletters, newspaper articles, press releases, reports, statistics, the University Act statutes, and Peak Student Handbooks (1985, 1989).
      Department of Athletics; Simon Fraser Student Society; Teaching Support Staff Union; Department of Political Science, Sociology and Anthropology; Wong, Stan; Loney, Martin; Walsh, Robert R.; Spencer, Ian; Strand, Kenneth; McTaggart-Cowan, Patrick
      - Photocopies from fonds, #1-106, 1965 - 1969; F-223-1-2-2-1 (Archival box - standard 223-10)
      - Photocopies from fonds, #107-265, 1965 - 1976; F-223-1-2-2-2 (Archival box - standard 223-10)
      - Photocopies from fonds, #266-408, 1965 - 1967; F-223-1-2-2-3 (Archival box - standard 223-10)
      - Photocopies from fonds, #409-519, 1967 - 1969; F-223-1-2-2-4 (Archival box - standard 223-10)
      - Photocopies from fonds, #520-656, 1966 - 1985; F-223-1-2-2-5 (Archival box - standard 223-10)
      - Photocopies from fonds, #657-838, 1966 - 1998; F-223-1-2-2-6 (Archival box - standard 223-10)
      - Photocopies from fonds, #839-949, 1965 - 1994; F-223-1-2-2-7 (Archival box - standard 223-10)
      - Photocopies from fonds, #950-1074, 1965 - 1971; F-223-1-2-2-8 (Archival box - standard 223-11)
      - Photocopies from fonds, #1075-1200, 1966 - 2003; F-223-1-2-2-9 (Archival box - standard 223-11)
      - Photocopies from fonds, #1201-1343, 1970 - 1981; F-223-1-2-2-10 (Archival box - standard 223-11)
      - Photocopies from fonds, #1344-1368, 1965 - 1980; F-223-1-2-2-11 (Archival box - standard 223-11)
    - Yellow notebook, 2000 - 2004; F-223-1-2-3; 2 cm of textual records; The Archives previously arranged and described the president’s records up to 1985 as fonds F-27. In November 2004, F-27 was superseded by F-193. Appendix G of F-193 contains a concordance between all F-27 files and the corresponding F-193 number.
      Sub-sub-series consists of one yellow notebook with working notes taken by Hugh Johnston during the preparation of Radical Campus. The notebook includes numbered random notes. Pages are numbered 1-232. Interview subjects include Stan Wong, Colin Yerbury, John Buchanan, Percilla Groves, Arvid Grants, John Edmonds, John Conway, Lolita Wilson, Don Devoretz, Roger Blackman, Jerry Zaslove, John Munro, Len Berggren, John Tietz, Theodor D. Sterling, and Evan W. Alderson. Records include numbered random notes (p. 5-51); a rough indexing of The Peak articles (p.65-77); a rough indexing of the photocopies from fonds (p. 79-96); rough notes from interviews (p. 97-128); notes from F-79 SFU Faculty Association fonds and F-27 Office of the President fonds (p. 155-179); interview notes (p. 180-217); and odd notes interspersed throughout the notebook.
      Wong, Stan; Yerbury, J. Colin; Buchanan, John; Groves, Percilla; Grants, Arvid; Edmonds, John; Conway, John; Wilson, Lolita; Devoretz, Don; Blackman, Roger; Zaslove, Jerald; Munro, John M.; Tietz, John H.; Berggren, Len; Sterling, Ted; Alderson, Evan W.
      - Yellow Notebook, pages #1-232, 2000 - 2004; F-223-1-2-3-1 (Archival box - standard 223-11)
    - Red notebook, 2000 - 2004; F-223-1-2-4; 2 cm of textual records
      Sub-sub-series consists of one red notebook with working notes on archival sources taken by Hugh Johnston during the preparation of Radical Campus. Pages are numbered 1 to 411. Academic departments documented include Physics, Languages, Mathematics, Computing Science, Psychology, Fine and Performing Arts, Chemistry, English, Communications, Library, Kinesiology, History, Philosophy, Economics, PSA, Biology, Criminology, Geography, Archaeology, and Education.
      Department of Physics; Department of Languages, Literature and Linguistics; Department of Mathematics; School of Computing Science; Department of Psychology; School for the Contemporary Arts; Department of Chemistry; Department of English; School of Communication; University Library; Department of Biomedical Physiology and Kinesiology; Department of History; Department of Philosophy; Department of Economics; Department of Political Science, Sociology and Anthropology; Department of Biological Sciences; School of Criminology; Department of Geography; Department of Archaeology; Faculty of Education
      - Red Notebook, pages #1-411, 2000 - 2004; F-223-1-2-4-1 (Archival box - standard 223-11)
  - Background material - Academic Departments, Women's Movement and the Epilogue, 1962 - 2004; F-223-1-3; 30 cm of textual records
    Sub-series consists primarily of photocopied source material about academic departments, and the Women's Movement. It also consists of source material for the Epilogue of Radical Campus. Subjects, activities and events documented include academic freedom and tenure; faculty appointments; prominent members of the SFU community; student activism; faculty and student associations; the development and expansion of SFU; and the Women's Movement. Sub-series includes briefs, reports, correspondence, discussion papers, memoranda, minutes, working papers, and newspaper and journal articles.
    - Academic departments and faculties, 1962 - 2003; F-223-1-3-1; 22 cm of textual records; The index for this material is in F-223-1-1-3: Yellow notebook.
      Sub-sub-series consists of photocopied material relating to the development and administration of academic departments; and the appointment, promotion, and tenure of faculty. Hugh Johnston numbered most of the pages and created an index to this material. Subjects, activities, and events documented include the Academic Freedom and Tenure Committee; the Appointment Committee; the Joint Committee on Salaries, Promotions and Tenure; the SFU Faculty Association; faculty appointments; the CAUT Censure; sabbatical leave; PSA dismissals; foreign scholars; departmental reviews; the University Development Committee; the development of academic research centres and institutes; faculty members; culturally significant individuals, groups and movements of the 1960s; student activism and Students for a Democratic Society (SDS). Sub-sub-series includes appointment notices; selected chapters of an unpublished anthology of essays; correspondence; draft policy statements; printed emails; faculty handbooks; interview transcriptions; discussion papers; list serve postings; memoranda; minutes; printed material from online newsletters, newspapers, magazines, and encyclopedias; newspaper and journal articles; reports; and working papers.
      Simon Fraser University Faculty Association; Academic Freedom and Tenure Committee; Canadian Association of University Teachers; Department of Political Science, Sociology and Anthropology; University Development Committee; Students for a Democratic Society
      - Reference material, unnumbered, 1975; F-223-1-3-1-1 (Archival box - standard 223-12)
      - Reference material, # -128, 1972 - 1985; F-223-1-3-1-2 (Archival box - standard 223-12)
      - Reference material, #129-232, 1985; F-223-1-3-1-3 (Archival box - standard 223-12)
      - Reference material, #233-330, 1985 - 2003; F-223-1-3-1-4 (Archival box - standard 223-12)
      - Reference material, #331-435, 1965 - 2003; F-223-1-3-1-5 (Archival box - standard 223-12)
      - Reference material, #436-540, 1967; F-223-1-3-1-6 (Archival box - standard 223-12)
      - Reference material, #541-667, 1967 - 1970; F-223-1-3-1-7 (Archival box - standard 223-12)
      - Reference material, #668-757, 1966 - 1986; F-223-1-3-1-8 (Archival box - standard 223-12)
      - Reference material, #758-813, 1962 - 1980; F-223-1-3-1-9 (Archival box - standard 223-12)
      - Reference material, #814-961, 1966 - 1978; F-223-1-3-1-10 (Archival box - standard 223-13)
      - Reference material, #962-1062, 1966 - 2001; F-223-1-3-1-11 (Archival box - standard 223-13)
      - Reference material, #1063-1187, 1964 - 2000; F-223-1-3-1-12 (Archival box - standard 223-13)
      - Reference material, #1188-1287, 1966 - 1984; F-223-1-3-1-13 (Archival box - standard 223-13)
      - Reference material, #1288-1369, 1965 - 1981; F-223-1-3-1-14 (Archival box - standard 223-13)
      - Reference material, #1370-1517 and attachment G, 1964 - 1999; F-223-1-3-1-15 (Archival box - standard 223-13)
    - Women's Studies and the Women's Movement, 1968 - 2001; F-223-1-3-2; 5 cm of textual records; The latter incomplete sequence of pages, 789-824, is material that Hugh Johnston relocated from F-223-1-2-2: Photocopies from fonds. The index for this material is in F-223-1-2-3: Yellow notebook.
      Sub-sub-series consists of photocopied material relating to the Women's Movement, SFU's early feminists, and the development of the Women's Studies Department. This material contains two numerical sequences of pages: from 1-166 and from 789-824 (with gaps). Subjects, activities and events documented include the Committee on the Status of Women for the Association of Universities and Colleges of Canada; the Status of Women Council; the American Sociological Association; the Working Women’s Association; the Vancouver Women's Caucus; Edmonton's Women's Liberation Movement; President Pauline Jewett; Margaret Benston; Andrea Lebowitz; Frances Wasserlein; the Women's Studies Curriculum Committee; and the Women's Studies Program. Records include briefs, minutes, correspondence, discussion papers, magazine articles, newsletters, proposals, and reports.
      Department of Gender, Sexuality, and Women's Studies; Association of Universities and Colleges of Canada. Committee on the Status of Women; Status of Women Council; American Sociological Association; Working Women's Association; Vancouver Women's Caucus; Women's Liberation Movement (Edmonton); Benston, Maggie; Jewett, Pauline; Lebowitz, Andrea; Wasserlein, Frances
      - Reference material, #1-129, 1968 - 1999; F-223-1-3-2-1 (Archival box - standard 223-13)
      - Reference material, #130-167, 1969 - 1990; F-223-1-3-2-2 (Archival box - standard 223-13)
      - Reference material, #789-838 [with gaps], 1985 - 2001; F-223-1-3-2-3 (Archival box - standard 223-14)
    - Index and material for the Epilogue, 1963 - 2004; F-223-1-3-3; 3 cm of textual records
      Sub-sub-series consists of photocopied material relating to the overall growth and transformation of the university in its first forty years. Subjects, activities and events documented include Burnaby Mountain Community Development; the CAUT Censure; Continuing Studies; external grants; governing bodies; Harbour Centre; the dismissal hearings for Nathan Popkin; the SFU Pipe Band; research grants; the Segal Graduate School of Business; SFU Surrey; Tech BC; support staff; and space allocation. Sub-sub-series includes annual reports; briefs; budgets; reports; correspondence; discussion papers; an index of material for chapters 4, 5 and 9 of Radical Campus; newspaper articles; statistics; and working papers.
      SFU Community Trust; Popkin, Nathan; SFU Surrey; Technical University of British Columbia; Canadian Association of University Teachers; Continuing Studies; Segal Graduate School of Business
      - Reference material and index, 1963 - 2004; F-223-1-3-3-1 (Archival box - standard 223-14)
      - Reference material, 1968 - 2004; F-223-1-3-3-2 (Archival box - standard 223-14)
  - Background material - Political Science, Sociology, and Anthropology Department, 1966 - 2004; F-223-1-4; 28 cm of textual records
    Sub-series consists primarily of photocopied material related to the trusteeship over the PSA department, the PSA Strike, and the subsequent dismissal of eight faculty members of the PSA department. Subjects, events and activities documented include the PSA Tenure Committee; the SFU Faculty Association; the Academic Freedom and Tenure Committee and statements; the CAUT Committee of Inquiry and motion of censure; the American Anthropological Association (AAA) ad hoc committee to investigate the SFU dispute; the Canadian Sociology and Anthropology Association (CSAA)'s boycott of SFU; the American Sociological Association ad hoc committee on the SFU dispute; the Canadian Political Science Association (CPSA)'s position; the Association of University and Colleges of Canada (AUCC)'s Committee on Academic Freedom; the Palmer Committee decision; the Rosenbluth Committee Report; the Supreme Court of BC in Wheeldon vs. SFU; and the university administration's actions under Presidents Kenneth Strand and Pauline Jewett. Sub-series consists of reports, issues of the Peak, minutes, memoranda, abstracts, press releases, correspondence, research notes, telegrams, newsletters, newspaper articles, strike bulletins, CAUT bulletins, book excerpts, journal articles, and printed online material.
    Department of Political Science, Sociology and Anthropology; Simon Fraser University Faculty Association; Canadian Association of University Teachers; American Anthropological Association; Canadian Sociology and Anthropology Association; American Sociological Association; Canadian Political Science Association; Association of Universities and Colleges of Canada; Palmer, Earl E.; Rosenbluth, Gideon; Wheeldon, Prudence; Strand, Kenneth; Jewett, Pauline
    - PSA strike - photocopied issues of the Peak, 1968, vol. 1, F-223-1-4-0-1 (Archival box - standard 223-14)
    - PSA strike - photocopied issues of the Peak, 1968, vol. 2, F-223-1-4-0-2 (Archival box - standard 223-14)